<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Queen Mary: the humble salutation, and faithful greeting of the widow Whitrowe With a vvarning to the rulers of the earth, before the Day of the Lord breaks forth, that shall burn as an oven, and all the wicked, and all the ungodly shall be as stubble: the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.</title>
            <author>Whitrowe, Joan.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2037</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220184</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831607</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831607</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65943)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2046:46)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To Queen Mary: the humble salutation, and faithful greeting of the widow Whitrowe With a vvarning to the rulers of the earth, before the Day of the Lord breaks forth, that shall burn as an oven, and all the wicked, and all the ungodly shall be as stubble: the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.</title>
                  <author>Whitrowe, Joan.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Signed at dated at end: Joan Whitrowe. Putney-Park, the 14th. of Decem. 1690.</note>
                  <note>Print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary --  II, --  Queen of England, 1662-1694 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1689-1694 : William and Mary) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Judgment Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Warnings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36072:1"/>
            <p>TO Queen Mary: THE Humble Salutation, AND FAITHFUL GREETING OF THE Widow Whitrowe.</p>
            <p>WITH A WARNING TO THE RULERS of the Earth, BEFORE The Day of the LORD breaks forth, that ſhall burn as an Oven, and all the Wicked, and all the Ungodly ſhall be as Stubble: <hi>The Mouth of the LORD hath ſpoken it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:36072:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36072:2"/>
            <head>TO Queen MARY: THE Humble Salutation, AND FAITHFUL GREETING OF THE Widow Whitrowe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>LET <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN MARY</hi> Live for ever, which is the deſire of my Soul to <hi>GOD</hi> for Thee, That the Crown of Righteouſneſs Thou mayſt Wear, and be Adorned with the rich Jewels of Eternal Life; [which are the Heavenly Vertues of <hi>GOD</hi> in Chriſt] and in Order thereunto, my Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Requeſt to the Queen, is, That She may live in the Fear of the LORD, that She may be Rich in Good Works, that She may take the Apoſtles Advice to the Primitive Chriſtians, after they were called from their Heatheniſh Ways, into that Honourable Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſion of the Chriſtian Life: <hi>Not faſhioning your ſelves,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as you did in the former Vanities, in the days of your Ignorance, but as He that hath called you, is holy; ſo be ye holy in all manner of your Life
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36072:3"/>and Converſation;</hi> as it is written, <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy:</hi> And take the holy Women in former Ages for your Example, <hi>Whoſe Adorning was not that of coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Jewels, or rich Attire, but the Hidden Man of the Heart;</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſt in you the Hope of Glory:</hi> And ſurther, ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> Tim. Chap. 2. <hi>Let Men pray every where, lifting up pure hands without wrath or doubting: Likewiſe alſo, the Women, that they array them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in comely Apparel, with ſhame-fac'dneſs and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, not with broidred Hair, or Gold, or Pearls, or coſtly Apparel, but as becometh Women that profeſſes the Fear of GOD with Good Works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is more, O Queen, than a pretended out-ſide Holineſs of Bodily Worſhip, and voluntary Humility; and thoſe that come no further, than to follow the Precepts and Commandments of Men, may be vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puft up in Pride and high-mindedneſs; and then in that Spirit, they are no more but as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Silly Women, ever learning, but never come to the Knowledge of the Truth;</hi> and this is but the out-ward Court, where the worſt of Men and Women may come, as that Pious Man, Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> Charged, ſaying, <q>Look you be not found in the Out-ward Court, but a Worſhipper within the Temple, before the Altar; for, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> Chriſt will meaſure all thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his Name, and call themſelves his People, and the out-ward Worſhippers He will leave out: The Out-ward Court, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> is the formal Chriſtian, whoſe Religion lyes in performing the out-ſide Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſtianity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Let the Queen be pleaſed to hear this Good Mans humble Confeſſion, which he made a little before his Death, (tho' a Preacher 40 Years before the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi>) to one of his Friends that challeng'd a Promiſe made by him: He Reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <q>That he had not writ, and yet could not charge
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36072:3"/>himſelf with any Breach of Promiſe; for, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> I did begin to write, but when I came to write of Sanctification, that is, of the New Creature, which <hi>GOD</hi> formeth by his Spirit in every Soul, which He doth truly regenerate: I found ſo little of it wrought in my ſelf, that I could ſpeak of it only as Parrots, by Rote, and without the Knowledge and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of what I might have expreſs'd; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I durſt not preſume to proceed any further up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. And <hi>Added:</hi> I muſt tell you, we do not well underſtand what Sanctification and the New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is, it is no leſs than for a Man to be brought to an intire Reſignation of his Will to the Will of <hi>GOD,</hi> and to live in the Offering up of his Soul, continually in the Flames of Love, as a whole burnt Offering to Chriſt: And how little <hi>(ſays he)</hi> are many of thoſe who profeſs Chriſtianity experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally acquainted with this Work in their Souls?</q>
               </p>
               <p>A Man worthy of Honour: I queſtion not, but HE that gave him that ſight, brought him into a good Meaſure of the Life thereof, before he depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Life: and I heartily wiſh; yea, with all my Heart, and with all my Soul, that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> together with all the reſt of the Churches of what ſort ſoever, that bears the Name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, were in the Life of what this humble Man had the ſight of; then ſhall Wars ceaſe, when HE comes to Reign, whoſe Right it is; <hi>GOD</hi> over all Bleſſed for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, O Queen, Live for ever in this Life, which this Humble Man had the ſight of, that is the New Creature, born again; not of that which is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, but of the incorruptible Life of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who ſaid to <hi>Nichodemus, A Man muſt be born again, before he can enter into the Kingdom of GOD.</hi> But this was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36072:4"/>a Myſtery to him: <hi>For</hi> ſaid he, <hi>How can this be? Can a Man enter again into his Mothers Womb?</hi> So ignorant was he of the Heavenly Life, tho' a Ruler in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And I wiſh too too many that are wiſe in their own eyes, be not covered with this Cloud of Ignorance and Errour, that whilſt they Govern and Teach others, they themſelves have need to be taught.</p>
               <p>But, O Queen, live thou for ever in the holy, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſelf-denying Life of Chriſt; that a holy Pattern thou mayſt be, that thy Light may ſo ſhine, that all may ſee thy good Works, and give Glory to <hi>GOD</hi> that ever the Queen came into this Nation. In Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to this, I humbly intreat the Queen, That She believe not every Spirit that ſhall come to her, and ſay, <hi>It belongs to the Queens Dignity to take State up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, and to go in Rich and Gorgious Attire:</hi> Know this, O Queen, That there can be no more ſaid to the Ignorant Heathen, that knows not <hi>GOD:</hi> But I hope the Queen will have more of the Wiſdom of <hi>GOD,</hi> than to ſuffer her innocent Spirit to be betrayed, or captivated into ſuch Trumpery and fooliſh Fopperies; for She being a Chriſtian, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is to be her Teacher, and <hi>Christ</hi> to be her Pattern: And where was His <hi>State,</hi> and His Gorgious Apparel? He wore a plain Garment without a Seam: It's true, whilſt they were a Crucifying Him, they put on a purple Garment to ſcoff and deride His humble ſelf-denying Life: And doth not the Chriſtians of our Times do the ſame? And where was His <hi>State;</hi> for He often ſate on the Ground; and who His Companions? Poor Fiſher men, who left all and followed Him; the Lame, and the Blind, poor Publicans, which were heavy laden; their Sins being a Burden too heavy for them to bear, and ſo were glad of a Phyſitian to Cure them of their Maladies; but indeed the proud high-minded
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36072:4"/>
                  <hi>Phariſees,</hi> were offended with Him for this humility. But the Queen keeping in the humility of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> She will place her Affections upon more high and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime things; for the Spirit of the <hi>LORD,</hi> is a <hi>noble Spirit,</hi> High and Mighty above all tranſitory Things.</p>
               <p>The Queen being of His Spirit, will be the ſame: She'll ſcorn the Pomps and Pleaſures of a poor, dirty, periſhing World: She'll place her Delights upon more high and excellent things, than the Pomps and Vanities of this wicked World, wherein the worſt of Heathens takes delight; but for the beſt of them, they mind more Divine and Heavenly things: As <hi>Socrates,</hi> (that Divine Philoſopher;) <q>Fine and rich Cloaths, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> are only fit for Commedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</q> and being demanded from what things Men and Women ought to refrain, <q>From Pleaſures, <hi>ſaid he;</hi> temperate Perſons become the moſt Excellent; they eat that which neither hurts the Body nor Mind, and that which is eaſy to be got: The only and beſt way <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> to Worſhip <hi>GOD,</hi> is to mind and obey whatſoever He Commands; that the Souls of Men and Women may pertake of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature; that <hi>GOD</hi> is ſeen of the Vertuous Mind, that by waiting upon Him, they are United unto Him in an acceſſible place of Purity and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs; <hi>GOD</hi> hath aſſerted them always to be near unto Him.</q> Theſe are they that were worthy of the Name of Chriſtians, becauſe they imitate Him in their Lives, who were Plain, Humble, and Self-denying, like Chriſt their <hi>LORD;</hi> who ſaid, Learn of me, Learn of me; <hi>ſaith he,</hi> that was <hi>GOD</hi> over all Bleſſed for ever; yet, humbled himſelf to the Death, yea, the Death of the Croſs; before whom, let all Kings, Queens, and Potentates of the Earth lick the Duſt; before Him who is <hi>LORD</hi> and Governor of all things, from whom
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36072:5"/>the greateſt Monarch in the Earth hath his Breath, and He can take it away at his pleaſure; therefore, who ſhall not ſear Him, the <hi>Everlaſting;</hi> before whom, all Nations are as a drop of a Bucket. Yea, let the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and Earth tremble before Him, who ſhall lay all Fleſh in the Duſt, and then, Where ſhall its Glory be? Therefore, O Queen, live for ever in this plain, innocent, and humble Life of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who made Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of no reputation; and, <hi>ſaid He,</hi> to his Diſciples, (when they were ſtriving for the Maſterſhip, one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the other;) <hi>The Gentiles which bear Rule, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Lordſhip one over the other, but with you, it muſt not be ſo; but he that is chiefeſt among you, let him be Servant to all.</hi> And this did He in Practice, as well as Doctrine, when He waſhed His Diſciples feet; and ſo left them and all His followers an Example to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low His Steps: He did not ſay, follow this Man, or that Man; no, nor the footſteps of the Flock; no, for He knew that all Men might Err, therefore he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and commanded, ſaying, <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly, and you ſhall find reſt for your Souls.</hi> Oh! the Treaſure of Treaſures, the Pearl of great Price, that whoſoever hath it, will Sell all for it; all their periſhing Glories, with all their fading Delights; and count it all, but dung and droſs, for the Excellency of this Life in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, hear O Princeſſes, and give Ear ye Ladies of the periſhing Honours of this World; Did <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the <hi>LORD,</hi> and only Saviour, the Immaculate Lamb of <hi>GOD</hi> that takes away the Sins of the World; Conſecrate a Way for you, through His Agonies of Sorrows, and Griefs, bitter Death, and bloody Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for you to live a Life of Vanities and Pleaſures, the Pomps and Pride of Life, the Luſt of the Fleſh, and the Luſt of the Eye? Was all his ſtrong Cries,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36072:5"/>Groans, Sighs and Sobs, Watchings and Faſtings, cruel Mockings and Scourgings; expoſing Himſelf to all the Malice that Men or Devils could Invent, Was all theſe Miſeries to End here? Or was this to be the End of all, to faſten you to your curſed Plays, with your whole Life of ſinful Pleaſures? Ye careleſs Daughters, ye Women that are at Eaſe, be aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, pluck off your Gorgious Attire, put on Sackcloth, and cover your Heads with Aſhes, and ſit on the Ground; and from thence, take up a deep and heavy Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the miſeries that are coming upon you; when your Songs ſhall be turned into Howlings, your Joys into Heavineſs and bitter Lamentations; which ſhall be the Reward of all your vain and wicked Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that hath been ſpent in vain and wicked Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; of which precious time, the leaſt moment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of upon a dying Bed, is more than the Gold of <hi>Ophir. Then ſhall you call,</hi> ſaid the <hi>LORD, but I will not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. You ſhall ſeek Me early, but you ſhall not find Me.</hi> And, why? <hi>Becauſe you hated Knowledge, and did not chuſe the Fear of the LORD: You would have none of my Counſel, but deſpiſed all my Corrections, therefore ſhall you Eat of the Fruit of your own ways, and be filled with your own Devices: For Eaſe, ſlayeth the fooliſh, and the Proſperity of Fools deſtroyeth them; but they that obey Me,</hi> ſaith the <hi>LORD, ſhall dwell ſafely, and be quiet from the fear of Evil,</hi> Prov. 1. Chap. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider theſe things, <hi>all you that forget GOD, leaſt I tear you in pieces and there be none to deliver you,</hi> ſaith the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, O Queen, live for ever! The way for the Queen to obtain this Everlaſting and Eternal Life, is to watch againſt the Evil of her own Heart, for ſo the <hi>LORD</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, ſaying, Watch, Watch, Watch, which He fulfill'd before He gave it out to others, when He was led into
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36072:6"/>the Wilderneſs, and there thrice tempted, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaid, <hi>He was in all things tempted as we are, yet without ſin, that He might be able to ſuccour us that are tempted:</hi> For this know, O Queen, it is no ſin to be tempted; but the ſin is to yield to the temptation; as ſaith the Prophet, <hi>When ſinners inticeth thee, conſent not thou unto them;</hi> therefore the <hi>LORD</hi> commanded to make the Defence ſtrong, double your VVatch; yea, treble your VVatch; and ſaith the Prophet, <hi>A threefold Cord cannot eaſily be broken.</hi> O how good is the <hi>LORD,</hi> to give us theſe Heavenly Precepts, and not only ſo, but to be our Strength in weakneſs. <hi>Thou haſt covered our Heads in the Day of Battle, when the Enemy hath come in like a Flood. Thou haſt lifted up Thy Standard againſt him, Glory he unto Thee for ever.</hi> Thus hath the <hi>LORD</hi> ſtood by them that fear him in all Ages, to be their Preſerver from the Snares and Temptations of the Devil; but then, they muſt be found in His VVay, otherwiſe, He is not engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to preſerve them: The VVay of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is His daily <hi>CROSS; You cannot be my Diſciples,</hi> ſiath He, <hi>Except you deny your ſelves, and take up My Croſs and follow Me;</hi> (VVhether muſt we follow Him?) Through all the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels of his Soul; as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet propheſied of him, ſaying, <hi>He ſhall ſee of the Travel of his Soul, His righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soul ſhall be ſatisfied;</hi> and in vain is all your Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Hearing, Praying, and Praiſing out of his Holy, Pure, and Incorruptible Life. And further of his Life, you may read in <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Propheſy of Him, how <hi>He was a Man of Sorrows, and was well acquainted with Griefs;</hi> and after he came into the World, in the Holy Hiſtory of his Life of temptations and miſeries, he ſaith, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life; none can come to the Father, but by Me, and he that climbs up another way is a Thief and a Robber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Way, O Queen! Then through his bitter Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36072:6"/>a Way indeed, that at the firſt Entrance, his Viſage ſeems black, and his Form to be without Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; yet is he the Beloved of our Souls, and the Chiefeſt among Thouſands, to them that have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Him through the many Tribulations, and have waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their long-ſuffering Robes, and made them white in the Blood of the Lamb: <hi>Theſe ſhall walk with me,</hi> ſaith He, <hi>in White, for they are worthy; for becauſe you have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered with me, therefore ſhall you Reign with me for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that is Holy and True.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, at the firſt, you know, the Learning of any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, or lawful Art, it cannot be attained but with great Induſtry and hard Labour; ſo this inward Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Soul, at the firſt, ſaith the Prophet, <hi>She</hi> [meanng Wiſdom] <hi>will walk with him by crooked ways, and bring him into fear and dread, and torment him with her Diſcripline until ſhe have tryed his Soul, and hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him by her Judgments: Then will ſhe return the ſtrait way unto him, and comſort him, and ſhew him her ſecrets, and heap upon him the Treaſures of Wiſdom, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of Righteouſneſs:</hi> Oh! This was an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Man in the Work of <hi>GOD,</hi> on the Soul; this I bear Record, is the way of the <hi>LORD,</hi> which He takes to redeem Mankind to Himſelf, out of his fallen State: <hi>But,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>if he goes wrong, ſhe will forſake him, and give him over to his Deſtruction:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O Queen, live for ever in the holy and ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life of Chriſt; for be it known to the Queen, when I heard of the vain Paſtimes, and ſinful Pleaſures with the Exceſs of Finery, in Richneſs of Apparel, that was at the Court, on the Kings Birth Day, which was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by one of the Ladies at Court, to a Lady a near Relation of hers; which told me, that there was never ſeen ſuch coſtly Apparel at the Court. After I heard this, and that the Queen went to Plays, Oh how was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36072:7"/>my Soul bowed down before the <hi>LORD,</hi> crying bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to the <hi>LORD,</hi> that He would be pleaſed to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give the Queens Tranſgreſſion, as hoping it was not in the Queens Inclination, but overcome by the Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others: Oh Queen! Is this to return Thanks to the moſt High <hi>GOD,</hi> according to the great Benefits ſhe hath received? Is this to Anſwer the end of her Creation, and the King's ſafe Return from <hi>Ireland?</hi> Muſt all the Goodneſs of <hi>GOD,</hi> and his manifold Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, end here, in the Exceſs of Vanities, the Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of <hi>England,</hi> as Plays and Dancings, the Two grand In-lets to all other Abominations? I knew it once, to my Sorrow, as I could give a large Account thereof, the Influence thoſe curſed Vanities, as Pride, Plays, Dancing and Singing, had upon me when I was young; but in my Youth, the <hi>LORD</hi> had Mercy on me, and called me to himſelf, out of all thoſe ſinful Pleaſures, into the Pleaſure of Waiting and Attending upon Him who is alone Worthy, to have all our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Time, Love and Delights, whoſe Right it is; and for that end it was given us, to return it with that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Grace, that ſhall never have an end: For, O Queen,
<q>
                     <l>Wherein ſhould Youth take pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>But in ſeeking a Meaſure,</l>
                     <l>Of Wiſdoms ſaving Treaſure.</l>
                  </q> And ſaith Chriſt, <hi>ſeek and ye ſhall find, knock and it ſhall be opened unto you:</hi> But this know, O Queen, it muſt be a Heart-breaking ſeeking, that muſt find the <hi>LORD:</hi> an inward ſeeking; yea, more inward, than our moſt inward Parts. We muſt often retire alone, as Chriſt did from the Multitude, and inwardly into our own Souls, to the Spirit of <hi>GOD</hi> in us, waiting upon the Spirit,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36072:7"/>to receive Power to do the Will of <hi>GOD</hi> in all things; conſtantly watching againſt the Out goings of the Mind to any thing, but to <hi>GOD</hi> alone: This is waiting at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to receive the Promiſe of the <hi>FATHER.</hi> And in my ſeeking, I have found this to be the Way, in which <hi>GOD</hi> will be found in: Here I have found, and do ſind, the Spirit of Prayer and Supplications poured into my Soul; here I find my Heart and Mind taken off from all Viſibles, and ſet upon <hi>GOD</hi> alone; here I find my heart united to the <hi>LORD;</hi> here I find the height and depth of His Love, that hath ſo faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to Him, as a Nail is faſtned in the ſure place; ſo that height, nor depth, things preſent, or to come, ſhall ever be able to ſeparate me from the Love of <hi>GOD,</hi> which I have received in Chriſt my <hi>LORD,</hi> who hath given me the Victory over Death, Hell and the Grave; ſo that, here I can do as my Saviour hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me, <hi>Love my Enemies, and Pray for them that hate me;</hi> and ſo not to be overcome with Evil, but to overcome the Evil with the Good. <hi>Glory for ever be given to Thee my</hi> Soveraign LORD, <hi>and to Thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Power, from a Heart rended to pieces before Thee, in the ſence of Thy Gracious Goodneſs, and boundleſs Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours: Oh! When ſhall it be, that my Tongue ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ceaſe praiſing Thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this was the Way that all the People of the <hi>LORD</hi> ever ſound him in; as the Queen may be pleaſed to ſearch the Scriptures, and ſhe ſhall find what that Holy Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith; <hi>With my Soul have I deſired Thee in the night, and with my Spirit within me, will I ſeek Thee in the Morning: O</hi> LORD, <hi>we have waited for Thee, in the Way of thy Judgments: The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of our Souls is to Thee, and unto thy Name: Like as a Woman with Child, that draweth near to the Time of her Travail, is in ſorrow, and cryeth in her Pains, ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36072:8"/>have we been in thy ſight, O LORD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſorrows of Hell hath compaſſed me about; I eat Aſhes as my Bread, and mingled my Drink with my Tears:</hi> Beſides, Time would fail to Mention all the Travels of the Souls of the Righteous: But Queen <hi>Hesther,</hi> that Honourable Queen, who was worthy of the Dignity ſhe was brought to, for that very Act of deep Humiliation; who with a holy Zeal, and couragious Spirit, Commanded <hi>Mordecai,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Go and aſſemble all the Jews in</hi> Shuſhan, <hi>and faſt ye for me, and eat not, nor drink in three days, day nor night; I and my Maids will do the ſame, and ſo will I go to the King, which is not according to the Law, and if I periſh, I periſh:</hi> Now ſee the Effect of this holy Act; for it prevailed both with <hi>GOD</hi> and Man: It had Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to change King <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi>'s heart from a Lyon's to a Lambs; <hi>For this kind,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>can come out no other way, but by Faſting and Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus ſhall it be with Queen <hi>Mary</hi> if She fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows Chriſt her Pattern. In the firſt place, her Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion will be great within, bearing Rule over her own Will, Ways and Works, Words and Thoughts, not giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf the leaſt Liberty to any thing, that ſhall bring the leaſt Diſhonour to the holy Name of the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place, She ſhall have the Wiſdom of <hi>GOD</hi> to Govern her People, beginning firſt at the Court, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Fear of <hi>GOD,</hi> keeping all in Subjection by her pious Life, and heavenly Inſtructions, encouraging Vertue, and ſuppreſſing all Vice; and great Neceſſity there is for the Reformation to begin there: For by lamentable Experience, we have ſeen, that as it hath been at the Court, ſo it hath been, for the moſt part, throughout the Nation: Therefore, O Noble Princes,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36072:8"/>for the Glory of GOD and the Everlaſting welfare of thy Immortal Soul, and the Good of all theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; be not negligent in this great Work; and this know, O Queen, there is more required of you; that is, of KINGS, QUEENS, and POTEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATES of the Earth, than of others, for you ſtand in the place of <hi>GOD</hi> to the People: Therefore, the blood of all muſt lie at your Doors, if you do not quit your ſelves by your ſaithfulneſs to <hi>GOD</hi> and Man; for, <hi>ſaith</hi> Wiſdom, <hi>Mighty Men ſhall be mightily puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> Therefore, <hi>Hear O ye Kings and Queens, and Judges of the Earth: Give Ear, ye that Rule the Multitudes, and Glory in the multitude of People, for the Rule is given you of the</hi> LORD, <hi>and Power from the Moſt High, which will try your Works, and ſearch out your Inventions; for if you that are Officers of His Kingdom, judge not right, and keep not His Commandments, to walk after the will of</hi> GOD, <hi>horribly and ſuddenly will He appear unto you, and give you the reward of your Works; for He that is</hi> LORD <hi>over all, will ſpare no Mans Perſon, neither ſhall He ſtand in awe of any Mans Greatneſs.</hi> For He will take His Jealouſy for his Armour, and ſhall Arm the Creatures to be revenged of his Enemies, as might be ſeen in that aſtoniſhing, amazing, great and wonderful (never to be forgotten) Thunders which were lately in theſe parts of the World; and thoſe horrible Earthquakes beyond the Seas; for as by the greatneſs of His Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Power, He made all things, and upholds all things by the ſame; ſo by the Word of his Power, can He conſume us all, and turn all things into nothing; and yet in this Work will He put on Righteouſneſs for a Breaſt-plate, and take true Judgment inſtead of an Helmet; He will take Holineſs for an invincible Shield, He will ſharpen his fierce Wrath for a Sword, and and his Angels (who are his Miniſtring Spirits) in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36072:9"/>Flames of Fire, ſhall ſight with him againſt the unwiſe. Therefore, be wiſe, O ye KINGS, and underſtand; learn ye Judges of the Earth; ſerve the LORD in fear and rejoyce in trembling, kiſs the <hi>Son</hi> leaſt he be angry, and you periſh in your ways; for when His wrath ſhall ſuddenly burn, O then, bleſſed for ever will they be that put their whole truſt in Him; and that the latter may be your Portion, is the deſire of my Soul to <hi>GOD</hi> for you all,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your faithful Friend, and the <hi>LORD</hi>'s Servant, <hi>Joan Whitrowe.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>AND further, to the Queen, my deſire to <hi>GOD</hi> for her, is, That <hi>GOD</hi> would give her another Heart, a heart to walk in all the ways of the <hi>LORD,</hi> and that the <hi>LORD</hi> would pour out his Holy Spirit upon her, as He did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all His Anointed Ones; and that ſhe may be an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in His Hand to convert many to Righteouſneſs; then ſhall the Propheſy of <hi>Daniel</hi> be fulfilled on her, which ſaith, <hi>Thoſe that convert many to righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever more.</hi> And, O that <hi>GOD</hi> would touch the Hearts of them that follow the Queen, as He touched the heart of thoſe that followed <hi>Saul,</hi> after he was Anointed King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that the Spirit of the LORD would come upon the King and Queen, and all that belongs to them, as it came upon <hi>David</hi> after the <hi>LORD</hi> had Anointed him in the midſt of his Brethren; that by the Power of his Holy Spirit, they may follow the <hi>LORD</hi> fully, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> did; that they may be poſſeſſors of the good and holy Land of everlaſting Peace and Reſt for evermore.</p>
               <p>This is the Land that flows with Milk and Honey, but not a Land for outward pleaſures, but the inward ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhments
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36072:9"/>of the Soul, which is the reward of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, who follow their <hi>LORD</hi> through the ſtrait and narrow Way, which is the way to Eternal Reſt; as their <hi>LORD</hi> ſaid, <hi>Strait is the Gate, and narrow is the Way that leads to life, and few there be that finds it. Ah! but broad is the Way, and wide is the Gate that leads to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and many there be that goes therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed, to Fleſh and Blood, the Way to Life and Glory, ſeems ſtrait, and narrow at the firſt entrance, until the Soul is accuſtomed to bear the Yoke; but afterwards, it is Eternally true, as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>My Yoke is eaſy, and my Burthen light.</hi> Yea, for ever, I am a Witneſs, That in all His Ways are Pleaſantneſs, and in all His Paths are Peace.</p>
               <p>And this I declare, in the Power and Spirit of the <hi>LORD,</hi> there is no Tongue can ſpeak, Heart conceive, nor Pen can write the ſweet Repoſes, and Heavenly Enjoyments in the Raviſhments of His Love, which that Soul is a poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of, that keeps upon its Watch-Tower, whoſe Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in the Law of the LORD, Day and Night it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys Heaven, whilſt it is on Earth: Well might <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>A day in Thy Courts,</hi> O LORD, <hi>is more than a Thouſand elſewhere: I had rather be a door-keeper in the Houſe of the</hi> LORD, <hi>than to dwell in the Tents of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> and to this, <hi>Wiſdom</hi> anſwers, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed are thoſe that heareth me, watching daily at my Gates, and giving at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance at the Poſts of my Doors; for he that findeth me, findeth life, and obtaineth favour of the</hi> LORD. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in a holy Extaſy, cries out, <hi>O the height and depth, of the love of</hi> GOD; <hi>neither can it enter into the Heart of man, the things that</hi> GOD <hi>hath prepared for them that love Him.</hi> No certainly, not the men of this World, who have their Portions in this Life, which <hi>David</hi> deſired to be delivered from: But it entred into the Heart of <hi>Mary,</hi> when ſhe ſat ſo attentively at <hi>Jeſus</hi> Feet, to hear the precious Words that dropt from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36072:10"/>His Gracious Lips; where ſhe received the ſweet in-comes of His Eternal Love, whileſt the <hi>Martha</hi>'s of this World are hurried, incumbred, and diſtracted in their covetous, earthly Spirit, caring how to add Houſe to Houſe, Land to Land, and one Thouſand to another; and the other ſort, how to conſume what they have upon their luſts, in vain &amp; wicked recreations; and both theſe, diſpoſſeſſes the LORD of Life of his Right, and robs him of his Glory.</p>
               <p>And Farther, I am to acquaint the King and Queen, That the late <hi>Brewers</hi>-Tax falls heavy upon the Poor; the general Diſcourſe, is, the Rich will be richer, but the poor <hi>Brewers,</hi> will not be able to hold it; and for the poorer ſort of the People, if they can get Bread for themſelves and their Children, ſo; but for Drink, they ſay, they muſt drink Water; if the <hi>Parliament</hi> had been pleaſed to have laid it upon the Rich of all ſorts, and upon the Drunkards, the Feaſters, the Swearers, Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the Whoremongers, the proud Perſons that goes in Rich and Gorgious Attire; but above all, that Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Dreſs of the Head, the abomination of the Chriſtians, (which if the King and Queen will not bring down, <hi>GOD</hi> will, by his righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;) and thoſe curſed Play-houſes, and every one that goes to them; and the ſcant Meaſures, with the falſe Weights (which Robs the Poor of their Right) If it pleaſe the <hi>Parliament</hi> for the future, That theſe Taxes may be laid upon all theſe as heavy as Lead; and this will be for the Glory of <hi>GOD,</hi> the Good of Souls, and the Renown of the Kingdom: For theſe were the crying Sins of the <hi>Jews</hi> in their Day, which brought that heavy Deſtruction upon them, Pride and fulneſs of Bread. <hi>The Daughters of</hi> Zion <hi>are haughty,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 3. <hi>They go with their out-ſtretched-Necks, and their wanton Eyes, and then naming their abominable Attire,</hi> as may be read at large. But thoſe were the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36072:10"/>Rich, that are guilty of theſe abominations; <hi>For they Ground the Face of the Poor, and kept ſcant Meaſures, and falſe Weights, and ſold the needy for ſhooes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus far, I have cleared my Conſcience to <hi>GOD,</hi> and my Neighbour, in making the King and Queen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with theſe things: And I humbly deſire, That the King and Queen may do the ſame, by uſing all means poſſible to rectify theſe things; Firſt, in their own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, then by Proclamation, and Penalties; And I pray <hi>GOD,</hi> the King and Queen may not be ſlack in this their Work for the <hi>LORD; For it is written, Curſed is he that doth the Work of the</hi> LORD <hi>negligently;</hi> and that it may be done in the <hi>LORD</hi>'s time, for delays are dangerous: As Chriſt ſaid unto the <hi>Jews, You neglect the Weighty Matters of the Law, which ſhould have been done firſt, and not have left the other undone:</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Haggai,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thus ſpeaketh the</hi> LORD, <hi>the</hi> LORD <hi>of Hoſts, ſaying, this People ſay, the time is not yet come, that the</hi> LORD's <hi>Houſe ſhould be builded. Then came the Word of the</hi> LORD <hi>by the Miniſtry of the Prophet</hi> Haggai, ſaying, <hi>Is it time for your ſelves to dwell in your Ceiled-Houſes, and this Houſe lye waſte? Therefore thus ſaith the</hi> LORD <hi>of Hoſts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider your own ways in your Hearts; ye have ſown much, and brought in little; ye looked for much, but it came to little; and when ye brought it home, I did blow upon it; and why? ſaith the</hi> LORD <hi>of Hoſts, becauſe of mine Houſe that lies waſte, and ye run every Man into his own Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O King and Queen, is not this the preſent State of the Nation? I beſeech you conſider: My great Concern for the King and Queen, is, That they may not ſlip their Time, or the opportunity <hi>GOD</hi> hath put into their hands; for man hath but a Day or Hour given Him to do his work herein; and if he doth it not in that time, his Power is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36072:11"/>gone: Therefore it is, that the <hi>LORD</hi> calls ſo upon Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; ſaying, <hi>Whileſt it is to day, harden not your Hearts, as they did in the Provocation, when they tempted and proved Me, and ſaw My Works.</hi> For altho' they ſaw His wonderful Works, yet they believed Him not, but diſobeyed His righteous Laws; therefore, they never ſaw the good Land.</p>
               <p>We ſee what a dangerous thing Unbelief is; but <hi>David</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in <hi>GOD:</hi> I believed, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> therefore have I ſpoken; and then preſently, he longs to be upon returns, ſaying, <hi>What ſhall I render to the LORD for all His Mercies, and for all His Goodneſs? I will take the Cup of Salvation, and call upon His Holy Name: I will ſet no wicked thing before mine Eyes: I hate the work of them that turn aſide; it ſhall not cleave to me: I will walk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my Houſe with a perfect heart,</hi> Pſal. 101. and ſo he goes on to the end of the <hi>Pſal.</hi> which may be worth the King and Queens reading. And then after theſe Engagements, with many more; he promiſes to pay his Vows to the <hi>LORD,</hi> in the preſence of all: O that this Holy Spirit of Life, and Love, that was in <hi>David,</hi> who loved the <hi>LORD</hi> dearly, might Rule and Reign, and have the Dominion over all, in the King and Queen, and all that belongs to them: For why, elſe, am I thus concerned, that never was concerned with any King, Queen, or Prince, further than in the general to all, of that, which my Eyes hath ſeen come to paſs; and now with you in particular, of that which is to come? And that the Fame of your righteous Acts, may Sound to the furthermoſt parts of the Earth, to alarm the Nations to come up to the Mountain of the <hi>LORD</hi> of Hoſts; to learn His Ways, and to walk in the Paths of the <hi>GOD</hi> of <hi>Jacob;</hi> that as the Name of Chriſtians hath been a ſtink, a proverb, a by word of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach among the <hi>Turks;</hi> ſaying to <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men, <hi>Do you think I am a Chriſtian to falſify my word?</hi> So now by your holy Lives, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy VVorks, that Name may be a good Savour, that the Nations on your behalf, may have cauſe to Praiſe, Magnify, Worſhip, and Adore the Moſt High, and Everlaſting <hi>GOD</hi> for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is the earneſt Deſire of her, who doth humbly Proſtrate her ſelf at the Feet of Chriſt, on the King and Queens behalf:</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your humble Hand-maid,</hi> Joan Whitrowe.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Putney</hi>-Park, <date>the 14th. of <hi>Decem.</hi> 1690.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
